XIAOWEN NIE

Full Stack Software Engineer

she/her/hers niexiaowen90@gmail.com 520-288-4077 Bay Area, CA <u>LinkedIn</u> <u>GitHub</u> <u>Portfolio</u>

A passionate full stack software developer with an interest and background in web development and natural language processing, bringing hands-on experience in database architecture, optimization, web API and deductive reasoning.

SKILLS Python, JavaScript, React, Redux, Express, Flask, MongoDB, Postgres, HTML, CSS, Git, AWS

PROJECTS

Babetsy (React, Redux, Flask, SQLalchemy, HTML5 and CSS3)

Live Site | Github

A shopping website that allows users to add items to the shopping cart, place orders, add favorite items and search for items.

- Implemented an efficient order placing system with Flask to promptly check quantity of products against database
- Engineered clear, accessible and responsive user-centered features allowing users to update shipping information easily and leave feedback about purchased items using **React** and **Redux**
- Assembled efficient customer service Chatbot to enable instant service to customers over a wide range of topics

Esena (React, Redux, Flask, SQLalchemy, HTML5 and CSS3)

Live Site | Github

A project management tool for teams to collaborate on projects, assign tasks and view workflow capacities.

- Automated advance project organization utilizing multiple features (task, comments, calendar) to **prioritize** and discuss teamwork that enables better communication and collaboration between team members in **agile** environment
- Implemented an add team member feature through a **dynamic search** within application-wide and project scopes
- Incorporated a convenient calendar feature using React libraries allowing users to check daily tasks

NatureClikr (React, Redux, Express, Sequelize, AWS, HTML5 and CSS3)

<u>Live Site</u> | <u>Github</u>

A Flickr clone for users to browse and share images on nature topics, add and remove images from favorites, and leave comments.

- Centralized application state by populating data into Redux through AJAX fetch calls to RESTful API routes
- Applied multiple management functions like sorting and searching by keywords by using Express and React
- Integrated AWS S3 to fulfill efficient image uploads, storage and retrieval

Peacock Chinese Twitter Corpus (PCTC) (Flask, MongoDB, Twitter API, AWS, HTML5 and CSS3)

Site | Dataset An online Chinese Twitter corpus for academic studies

- Accelerated text search with accurate results by efficient text segmentation and indexing using ElasticSearch
- Built a large database of language data (1 million entries) collected through Twitter API with MongoDB
- Launched stable and secure application on AWS EC2 instance server

EXPERIENCE

Hammerhead and Oranges LLC, Linguist Sunnyvale, CA

2020-2021

- Developed online linguistic apps/tools for academic uses, *e.g.* Peacock Chinese Twitter Corpus (PCTC) utilized and highly recommended by linguistic professors and students
- Built and managed large linguistic databases using SQL and MongoDB to achieved efficient data query

University of Arizona, Teaching Associate & Research Assistant Tucson, AZ

2013-2017

- Taught language, linguistics and culture courses to undergraduate students as part of an instructional team
- Assisted in second language acquisition projects conducted by UA and Center for Applied Linguistics using Praat

EDUCATION

App Academy San Francisco, CA Full Stack Development

2022

• 6 months of intense training in computer science fundamentals, web development, frontend and backend engineering **University of Arizona** Tucson, AZ Ph.D. in *Linguistics*; minor in *Computational Linguistics* 2013-2019

- Conducted quantitative and qualitative linguistic research
- Substantial training and practice in language data analysis using NLTK, SpaCy, and Treebank, etc.

Hong Kong Polytechnic University Hong Kong M.A.

2011-2012

Xi'an International Studies University Xi'an, China B.A.

2007-2011